Gordimer mss., LMC 2355
Lilly Library
- Writings, (Box 4, folder 21 - Box 15, folder 80)
  - Rags and Bones - Something Out There (Box 13)
    - Something Out There [story collection]. Viking, 1983., Jan. 1982; Feb. 1981; Feb. 1980; July 1981; Feb. 1982 (Box 13, Folder 25-35)
      Original, draft and/or final versions of: At the Rendezvous of Victory, Jan. 1982, two versions; A City of the Dead, A City of the Living, Feb. 1981, seven versions, including unpublished shortened version titled "Tenure", and version for The New Yorker; A Correspondence Course, Feb. 1980; Crimes of Conscience, July 1981, two versions; Letter To His Father, three versions, proof from London Review of Books, photocopy of English translation of Kafka's letter from his father, German transcription with corrections probably by Arnulf Conradi, S. Fischer Verlag, research materials; Love Stories: Blinder and Terminal, Feb. 1982, two versions; Rags and Bones; Sins of the Third Age, Jan. 1982, two versions; Something Out There, one version, draft chapters, and research materials
      - Complete collection, with instructions to typist (Box 13, Folder 36)
      - Edited typescript from Penguin-Viking (Box 13, Folder 37-38)
  - Something Out There (cont'd) - Tanzania: People, Not Money (Box 14)
    - Something Out There [story collection] (cont'd) (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
      Proofs; list of stories, where and when published and corrections for French translation
    - Something Out There [film script],., Apr. 25, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Adapted by Hugh Cassirer from novella by Gordimer. First rough draft
    - Something Unexpected [short story]. (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Adapted from a chapter of novel Occasion for Loving and published in Cosmopolitan. Original[?] and final versions; tear sheet
    - Son-in-Law [short story],., May 1964 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Original version
    - Songololo [short story],., 1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Excerpted and adapted from novel A Sport of Nature. Final version
    - Sorting the Images from the Man. Commissioned by and published in Newsweek, and published in Africa Commentary,., Feb. 26, 1990; 1990 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Final version as sent to Newsweek; tear sheet from Newsweek; expanded version as sent to AC, titled: Letter from Johannesburg
    - The South Africa I Want [article]., 1988 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Published in Der Stern, Germany, 1988. Second draft
    - South Africa: The Way Writers Live Now [article]., Feb. 1977 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Commissioned by German radio - Südwestfunk, Feb. 1977. Original version; photocopy of final version, incomplete
    - South Africa: Towards a Desk Drawer Literature [address],., 1968 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      Given to the students of the University of the Witwatersrand and published in The Classic, v.2, no. 4 (1968). Draft
    - A South African Childhood [article],., early 1950s (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Published by The New Yorker. First of two autobiographical essays [See also: Leaving School: A Bolter and the Invisible Summer] Final version
    - Speak Out: The Necessity for Protest [lecture]., 1971 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      E.G. Malherbe Academic Freedom lecture, University of Natal, Durban, 1971 and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Final version as delivered
    - Spoils [short story]. (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Published in Granta and included in Jump and Other Stories. Proof from Granta
    - A Sport of Nature [novel]. J. Cape,; Knopf, 1987. (Box 14, Folder 14-22)
      Original manuscript; revised penultimate version; copy from which final version was typed
      - Proofs from J. Cape Ltd. (Box 14, Folder 23-24)
      - Notes, discarded pages, notes for copy editors, style sheet; research material (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
    - A Stinging Touch of Local Colour. Review of Local Colour by Stephen Gray., ca. 1975 (Box 14, Folder 27)
      Published in Rand Daily Mail, ca. 1975 Final version
    - Story from the Top Shelf [short story]. (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Stranger in Town [short story],., 1963 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Sweet Dreams Selection [short story],., 1950 (Box 14, Folder 30)
      Unpublished final version; final version
    - A Tang of Smoke and Indigo. Review of Aké: The Years of Childhood by Wole Soyinka., 1982 (Box 14, Folder 31)
      Published in New York Review of Books, 1982. Original draft; final version; proof from NYRB
    - Tanzania: People, Not Money [article],., 1973 (Box 14, Folder 32)
      Published in The Atlantic, 1973. Eight pages of notes; original version; second draft, with corrections in red ink by Claude Wauthier; final version
  - Tenants of the Last Tree House - You Name It, Untitled Writings (Box 15)
    - Tenants of the Last Tree House [short story]. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Published in The New Yorker and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Revised version, incomplete, lacking unchanged pages; revision for The New Yorker
    - The Termitary [short story],., June 1974 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Published in London Magazine and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version
    - A Third Presence [short story],., Nov. 1964 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Included in Livingstone's Companions. Original version
    - Three in a Bed: Fiction, Morals and Politics [lecture]. Ben Bellit Lecture, Bennington College., Oct. 4, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Published as a chapbook by Bennington College, 1991. Original manuscript; final version with additions
    - Through Time and Distance [short story],., late 50s or early 60s (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Published in The Atlantic and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Final version; tear sheets
    - Through Time and Distance [film script]. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Adapted from short story for director John Schlesinger. Original and final versions of synopsis
    - Time Did [short story],., Aug. 1976 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Published in London Magazine, November 1977 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version; photocopy of final version
    - Tourism [short story],., Mar. 1982 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Published in London Magazine, June 1983. Original and final versions
    - Town and Country Lovers [short story],., Aug. 1974 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Published in Harper's and Queen and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original[?] version; second/penultimate version; copy edited version; photocopy of last portion
    - Transkei: A Vision of Two Blood-Red Suns [article],., 1978 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Published in GEO 1978, with photographs by David Goldblatt and in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Photocopy of final version; a section apparently not published; notes; original annotated copy; research clippings
    - The Triumph of Memory. Review of Memory is the Weapon, by Don Mattera., Feb. 8, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      Published in The Star, Johannesburg, Feb. 8, 1988. Final version; tear sheet
    - The Two Souths--One World [article],., 1961; June 9, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      Published in The Observer, London, June 9, 1963. Original version; tear sheet from The Observer
    - Unchaining Poets [article]., Dec. 9, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      Published in The New York Times, Dec. 9, 1972. Clipping of article with Edward Gorey illustration
    - Unconfessed History. Review of Ah, But Your Country is Beautiful by Alan Paton., Feb. 1982 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      Published in The New Republic, Feb. 1982. Final version
    - The Value of a Conference. Introduction to Culture in Another South Africa, an anthology of conference papers given at the CASA Conference, Amsterdam,, Zed Books, London, 1989., 1977 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - A View of the Nile [travel article],., Dec. 1958; 1959 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      Published in The National and English Review, 1959. Final version
    - The Visit [short story]. (Box 15, Folder 17)
      Photocopy
    - Vital Statistics [short story]. (Box 15, Folder 18)
      Published in The Kenyon Review and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Original version; first revision; final version
    - Vladimir Ledochowski, Man of Two Worlds [article]., 1987 (Box 15, Folder 19)
      Published in a Polish emigré journal, 1987. Final version
    - Waterford School: The Riches of Human Variety [article]., 1966 (Box 15, Folder 20)
      Published in school magazine Vista, 1966. Final version
    - What Being a South African Means to Me [address]., 1977 (Box 15, Folder 21)
      Given to the students at University of Cape Town, 1977. Photocopy of text
    - What Happened to Burger's Daughter or How South African Censorship Works. Taurus,., 1980 (Box 15, Folder 22-27)
      Paperback; drafts; notes and materials concerning Publication Control Board; clippings about censorship
    - What is a Writer's Freedom [lecture]. (Box 15, Folder 28)
      Durban Indian Teachers' Conference. Original first version; photocopy of final version
    - When I Lost My Innocence [article]., 1980 (Box 15, Folder 29)
      Published in Swedish paper Akton Bladet, 1980. Final version
    - Where Do Whites Fit in? [article],., 1959 (Box 15, Folder 30)
      Published in Twentieth Century and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Final version
    - Who Writes? Who Reads? The Concept of a People's Literature [address/article]., Oct. 1987; Nov. 27, 1989; 1988; June 1990 (Box 15, Folder 31)
      Original manuscript, with two pages of notes; final version as delivered, Albert Pick Lecture, University of Chicago, Oct. 1987; shortened version for Dagens Nyeter, Sweden; revised version delivered at UNESCO Conference, Dakar, Senegal, Nov. 27, 1989; version delivered for Phi Beta Kappa "Literary Exercises," Harvard University, 1988; version delivered at African Literature Conference, Oxford University, June 1990
    - Why Haven't You Written? [short story],., June 1970 (Box 15, Folder 32)
      Published in The New Yorker and included in Livingstone's Companions. Original version
    - With Open Eyes [article]., 1989 (Box 15, Folder 33)
      Tribute to Helen Suzman in a festschrift, published on her retirement from Parliament in South Africa, 1989. Final version
    - Witwatersrand: A Time and Tailings [essay], 1967., 1973 (Box 15, Folder 34)
      Published by Optima with photographs by David Goldblatt. Expanded for preface to On the Mines, by Gordimer and Goldblatt, published by C. Struik, 1973.
      Two original versions; second draft; final carbon version, with instructions to printer in Goldblatt's hand; On the Mines proofs annotated by Gordimer and Goldblatt; notes; tear sheet from Optima; research material
    - The Worst Thing of All [short story],., Oct. 1963 (Box 15, Folder 35)
      Published in London Magazine and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Original version
    - The Writer in South Africa Today [speech]. The Race Relations Symposium,., 1968 (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - The Writer's Imagination and the Imagination of the State [address]. International P.E.N. Congress, New York,., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Writing and Writers in South Africa [speech/article]. (Box 15, Folder 38)
      Unknown where given or published. Original text as delivered; final version of article
    - Writing in Africa: Nadine Gordimer Interviewed by Stephen Gray and Phil du Plessis., September 1972 (Box 15, Folder 39)
      Published in New Nation, September 1972, vol. 6, no. 2. Copy of New Nation only
    - You Name It [short story],., July 1972; June/July 1976 (Box 15, Folder 40)
      Published in London Magazine, June/July 1976 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original and final[?] versions
    - You Name It [television script]. (Box 15, Folder 41)
      Draft
    - Untitled Works (Box 15, Folder 41)
      - Article. Critique of an unnamed South African literature book, n.d. Notes (Box 15, Folder 42)
      - Article. In defense of Salman Rushdie., 1990 (Box 15, Folder 43)
        Written for The Observer, London, 1990. First draft of original version
      - Article. Pertaining to sale of King Farouk's treasures., 1954 (Box 15, Folder 44)
        Unpublished, commissioned by William Shawn of The New Yorker. Final version
      - Article. Tribute to Alan Paton., 1988 (Box 15, Folder 45)
        Published in The Observer, London and in The Star, Johannesburg. Final version as sent to The Observer
      - Article. Tribute to Angus Wilson on his 70th birthday., 1983 (Box 15, Folder 46)
        Published in Twentieth Century Literature, USA, 1983. Final version
      - Blurb. For catalog published by Purnell announcing Charles Eglington's book Under the Horizon., ca. 1976 (Box 15, Folder 47)
      - Introduction to In a World They Never Made: Five Black South African Poets Write About Life in the White-Makes-Right Land of Apartheid., May 1972 (Box 15, Folder 48)
        Published Playboy. Tear sheet from Playboy, May 1972 (v.19, no.5).
      - Introduction to documentary films Maids & Madams and South Africa Belongs to Us. (Box 15, Folder 49)
        Text as spoken by Gordimer on film
      - Introduction to Sounds of a Cowhide Drum, poems by Oswald Joseph Mtshali., 1970 (Box 15, Folder 50)
        Carbon typescript of final version
      - Introduction to Uku-Bamba Amadola by Bettie du Toit., 1976 (Box 15, Folder 51)
      - Jacket quote for Two Dogs and Freedom., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 52)
        Black children's drawings and texts collected by Colphine Smuts of Open School, Ravan Press, 1986. Final version
      - Novel. Unfinished and untitled second novel, about. Typed., 1951 (Box 15, Folder 53)
      - Preface to Familiarity is the Kingdom of the Lost by Dugmore Boetie., 1969 (Box 15, Folder 54)
      - Preface to When We Are at Home We Dance All Round the House by Margareta Ekstrom. (Box 15, Folder 55)
      - Review of Anthills of the Savannah by Chinua Achebe., 1988 (Box 15, Folder 56)
        Published in New York Times Book Review and Weekly Mail, Johannesburg. Final version for NYTBR, marked with cuts for later publication in the Weekly Mail; proof from Weekly Mail, with note to editor.
      - Review of Episode, by Harry Bloom. (Box 15, Folder 57)
        Original rough draft; notebook.
      - Review of The Hajji and Other Stories by Ahmed Essop., 1978 (Box 15, Folder 58)
        Probably written for The Star, Johannesburg. Final version
      - Review of Hourglass by Danilo Kis., 1991 (Box 15, Folder 59)
        Published by The Observer, London, 1991. First draft; final version as sent to editor.
      - Review of Idanre and Other Poems by Wole Soyinka., 1967 (Box 15, Folder 60)
      - Review of Jo'burg, Sis by Barney Simon. (Box 15, Folder 61)
        Original draft; final version
      - Review of The Literature and Thought of Modern Africa by Claude Wauthier., 1967 (Box 15, Folder 62)
      - Review of The Medicine Man (Swifa Ya Nguvumali), by Hasani Bin Ismail., 2 February 1970 (Box 15, Folder 63)
        Published in African Studies (2 February 1970). Tear sheet
      - Review of The Mind of South Africa: The Story of the Rise and Fall of Apartheid by Allister Sparks., May 11, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 64)
        Published in The Observer, London, May 11, 1990. Final version
      - Review of Move Your Shadow by Joseph Lelyveld., 1985; Nov. 1985 (Box 15, Folder 65)
        Published in the New York Times Book Review. Shortened version published in Weekly Mail, Johannesburg, Nov. 1985 and titled: South Africa: Explaining, Rationalizing, Forgetting.
        Photocopy of first version; final version; final version with cuts for shortened version; proof from NYTBR, with corrections and annotations by editor Robert Silvers and Gordimer; shortened version for WM
      - Review of Olive Schreiner, a biography by Ruth First and Anne Scott., 1980; 1989 (Box 15, Folder 66)
        Published in the The Times Literary Supplement, 1980 and Le Monde, 1989. Published as a foreword to subsequent editions of the book. Photocopy; adapted version, for Le Monde
      - Speech and/or article. On use of languages in South Africa. (Box 15, Folder 67)
      - Speech. Protest meeting on the banning of seven young activists and of SASPU National, journal of the South African Students Press Union., 1982 (Box 15, Folder 68)
        Original version; final version, with changes; three clippings reporting event
      - Speech. Ruth First Memorial Meeting., 1982 (Box 15, Folder 69)
        First draft
      - Speech. Writers and Human Rights Conference, Toronto., Oct. 1981 (Box 15, Folder 70)
        Original draft
      - Speech. Graduation address, University of Cape Town., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 71)
        Reading copy
      - Speech. Graduation address, University of the Witwatersrand., Apr. 28, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 72)
        Original version with introductory note
      - Speech. Orientation Week address for Students Representative Council, University of the Witwatersrand., Feb. 8, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 73)
        Original and final versions
      - Speech. First line: I have a file on censorship... Probably mid to late 70s. (Box 15, Folder 74)
      - Speech. Launch of Ellen Kuzwayo's Call Me Woman and Sue Gordon's A Talent for Tomorrow: Life Stories of South African Servants., June 1985 (Box 15, Folder 75)
      - Speech. To South African P.E.N., n.d. Unpublished. (Box 15, Folder 76)
        Final version; fragment of appeal for release of Harry Bloom
      - Speech. Benefit evening in aid of the training scheme PROTEC., 1987 (Box 15, Folder 77)
        Final version as delivered
      - Speech. In honour of Pablo Neruda to the International Forum of Solidarity with the Culture of Chile, Torun, Poland., 1979 (Box 15, Folder 78)
        Unpublished. Original version as delivered
      - Speech. Opening of David Goldblatt's photographic exhibition "People and Things"., June 3, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 79)
        Reading version
      - Text. To accompany photographs published by Esquire., 1987 (Box 15, Folder 80)
- Diaries and Notebooks, (Box 15, folders 81 - 87)
  - Diary., 1934 (Box 15, Folder 81)
    Records the beginning of the illness that caused Gordimer's mother to take her out of school at age 11, during which time she began to write.
  - Notebook., early 1950s (Box 15, Folder 82)
    Notes for stories, including: A Bit of Young Life, A Long Walk from Rhodesia, Visit to a Bachelor, An Image of Success
  - Diary used as notebook., 1959-1964 (Box 15, Folder 83)
    Notes for Occasion for Loving and The Late Bourgeois World and other stories.
  - Two diaries and, containing sparse notes of when stories were finished, etc., 1967; 1968 (Box 15, Folder 84-85)
  - Pages from notebook., 1980 - 1984 (Box 15, Folder 86)
    Dates at top of each page are those when note was made; dates in margins record when story was actually written. Working notes, ideas, etc. mostly for stories included in Something Out There: Sins of the Third Age, Crimes of Conscience, A City of the Living, a City of the Dead, At the Rendezvous of Victory, Something Out There. Notes also for: Old Stock; Idea for unwritten story--One day, towards the end of my life...; White girl married to a black... first idea for what became the novel A Sport of Nature; Love 3, Blinder; Love 4, Bernie du Toit... (unwritten); Love 2, Terminal; Tourism
  - Notebook., 1986 - 1990 (Box 15, Folder 87)
    Contains all notes, chapter analysis, names, ideas for novel, record of quotations, etc. for My Son's Story. Also contains notes for stories included in Jump, and Other Stories that were written or noted while writing My Son's Story, including: My Father Leaves Home; Some Are Born to Sweet Delight; The Moment Before the Gun Went Off; Home; Comrades; A Journey; Keeping Fit. Miscellaneous other notes including those for an unpublished story A Piece of History.
- Miscellaneous
  - National Union of South African Students. Charter, newsletters, minutes, 50th Congress minutes (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - "New Philosophers" clippings (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Nadine Gordimer (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Plomer, William. "Charles Kingsley." (Box 16, Folder 5)
    For The Times Literary Supplement?
  - World Literature Today, Volume 52, No. 4 (Autumn)., 1978 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Contains article: African landscapes: The World of Nadine Gordimer, by John Cooke, p.533.
  - Miscellany (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Additions
  Papers acquired in 2002.
  - The Burger's Daughter - The House Gun (Box 16)
    - The Burger's Daughter [novel]. Viking,., 1979 (Box 16, Folder 8-9)
      Page proofs
    - The House Gun [novel]. Bloomsbury,., 1998 (Box 16, Folder 10-21)
      First part of original, pp. 1-97, with notes and corrections; draft; revised copy; printout before corrections; discarded pages; notes and corrections; version with additional pages; typescript with corrections, pp. 36-170.
  - The House Gun (cont.) - Living in Hope and History (Box 17)
    - The House Gun (cont.) (Box 17, Folder 1-13)
      Photocopies of draft pages; typed copy (version 2?); final typescript; final proof; notebook; sources; correspondence and trial translation into French; miscellaneous related materials.
    - July's People [screenplay]. Viking,., 1981 (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Adapted from novel for Roland Joffé, "never filmed"
    - Living in Hope and History: Notes From Our Century [collection of essays]. Bloomsbury,., 1999 (Box 17, Folder 15-20)
      Drafts
  - Living in Hope and History:… (cont.) - None to Accompany Me (Box 18)
    - Living in Hope and History:… (cont.) (Box 18, Folder 1-13)
      Drafts; hand-corrected typed version; corrections faxed to FSG [Farrar, Straus and Giroux]; notes and corrections; Master proof, 5/4/99; Master proof 6/14/99; jacket proof
    - My Son's Story [novel]. Bloomsbury,; Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1990. (Box 18, Folder 14-16)
      Final proofs; jacket proof
    - None to Accompany Me [novel]. Farrar, Straus and Giroux,., 1994 (Box 18, Folder 17-20)
      Original; hand-corrected typed version.
  - None to Accompany Me (cont.) - The Pickup (Box 19)
    - None to Accompany Me (cont.) (Box 19, Folder 1-9)
      Corrected revised draft; incomplete corrected typescript; discarded versions of various pages; final version from which proofs were corrected; notebook; notes; clippings.
    - The Pickup [novel]. Bloomsbury,., 2001 (Box 19, Folder 10-20)
      Original; second draft; typed version for word processing; typed part version with handwritten corrections; copy-edited version from FSG; drafts; rewrites.
  - The Pickup (cont.) (Box 20)
    - The Pickup (cont.) (Box 20, Folder 1-19)
      Rewrite copy; typescript with corrections; penultimate version; final printout 7/12/2000; final copy for publishing and proof reading; first pass pages master 3/30/01; proofs; second proofs (final) from FSG, June 2001; master pages 5/15/01; author galleys (incomplete); jacket; notebook.
  - The Pickup (cont.) - Writing and Being (Box 21)
    - The Pickup (cont.). Notes, sources, correspondence; clippings. (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Selected Stories [short story collection]. Viking Press, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    - Something Out There [story collection]. Viking,., 1983 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Final copy
    - A Sport of Nature [novel]. J. Cape,; Knopf, 1987. (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Incomplete draft?
    - Writing and Being [series: Charles Eliot Norton Lectures, 1994]. Harvard University Press, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 7-16)
      Notebook (sources); drafts; corrected typescripts; reading copies, Oct.-Dec. 1994; penultimate version; final version; final copy; proof; jacket design and correspondence.
  - Correspondence - Gutsche, Thelma, 1950-1973 (Box 29)
  - Russell and Volkening Correspondence (Box 22)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 22)
    - 1952 (Box 22)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 22)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 22)
    - 1958 (Box 22)
    - 1960 (Box 22)
    - 1961 (Box 22)